<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rstats on Sam Abbott</title>
    <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/tags/rstats/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rstats on Sam Abbott</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Sam Abbott</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/rstats/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuberculosis Incidence and Interventions in England and Wales, 1913-2016</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/tb-england-wales/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/tb-england-wales/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This interactive dashboard uses data on Tuberculosis incidence from 1913-1916 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tuberculosis-tb-annual-notifications-1913-onwards&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;released&lt;/a&gt; by Public Health England and combines it with data on the interventions against Tuberculosis that have been discovered/implemented over the last century. The data was cleaned and imported into R using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.samabbott.co.uk/tbinenglanddataclean/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tbinenglanddataclean&lt;/a&gt; R package, which also contains information on how to apply for additional data, scripts to clean data extracts and graphing functions to visualise them. The dashboard is a work in progress and additional interventions, new figures and increased interactivity will be added over time. For a full page view of the dashboard see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.seabbs.co.uk/shiny/TB_England_Wales&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;http://seabbs.co.uk/shiny/TB_England_Wales&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;1000&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to TB Modelling</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/intro_tb_models/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/intro_tb_models/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuberculosis in England and Wales</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/tb_england_wales/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/tb_england_wales/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Dive; Premiums on Valuation in the Property Partner Portfolio</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/deep-dive-pp-premiums/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/deep-dive-pp-premiums/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Previously I have looked at visualising the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.propertypartner.co/aboutus#/ourstory&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Property Partner&lt;/a&gt; portfolio using &lt;a href=&#34;https://public.tableau.com/views/PropertyPartnerPortfolioVisualisation/PropertyPartnerPortfolio?:embed=y&amp;amp;:display_count=yes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tableau&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/deep-dive-pp-open-house/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;explored their resale date from July 2017&lt;/a&gt;. In this post I will be exploring the &lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.propertypartner.co/open-house-august-2017/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;August Open House resale&lt;/a&gt; data focussing on property premiums over both initial and latest valuation. The code for this post is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/seabbs/propertypartner/blob/master/report/17-09-18-premium/latest_initial_premium.Rmd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Property Partner advertises returns by combining both projected capital and rental returns. Properties are held for 5 years at which point any capital gain can be realised. However, Property Partner provides a secondary market which allows capital returns to be realised by selling shares to other investors. The sale price of shares is set by the market, and may or may not depend on the underlying value of the property. This post will explore the premium that sales on the secondary market set on both the initial and latest valuations of properties in the Property Partner Portfolio, and how this has changed over time. A first step is to look at premiums over time, for each property, averaged over each month (as are all premiums in this post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-26-deep-dive-pp-premiums/fig1.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the above plot we see that in the first year of operation all properties had premiums above 0% over initial valuation, but since then several have traded with premiums that are continuously negative. The majority of these properties have maintained steady premiums over initial valuation but several devalued in the second half of 2017. A single property (5 flats, Dutch Quarter, Colchester) has consistently traded with a negative premium although this appears to be improving over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-26-deep-dive-pp-premiums/fig2.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike premiums over initial valuation, premiums over latest valuation appear to have decreased continuously over time for the majority of properties. This indicates that premiums are not completely adjusting for increases in property value, making it unlikely that those exiting early will fully realise capital gains. Both plots indicate a relationship between premiums and the date a property was made available for resale, with properties available earlier having higher premiums over both initial and latest valuation. The above plots are hard to interpret due to the number of properties in the portfolio, therefore the next step is to summarise the data by averaging premiums across all properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-26-deep-dive-pp-premiums/fig3.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw in the previous plots premiums over both initial and latest valuation were highest in 2015 and have since decreased. Since 2016 premiums over initial valuation appear to have stabilised between 5% to 10% and premiums over latest valuation appear to have stabilised between 0% to -8%. The relationship between premiums over latest and initial valuation is summarised in the following plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-26-deep-dive-pp-premiums/fig4.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the plots above there was some evidence that properties acquired at different dates traded differently. To investigate this the following plot shows the average monthly premium for properties launched in each year Property Partner has been operating, for both initial and latest valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-26-deep-dive-pp-premiums/fig5.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see that properties acquired earlier consistently trade at a higher premium over both initial and latest valuation. Whilst the trend in initial valuation may be driven by increased valuation this cannot be the case for latest valuation. Instead, it is likely that this is a function of scarcity due to the lower supply of earlier properties. It may also be the case that previous performance on the platform is valued. This plot also indicates that premiums over latest valuation have constantly fallen for all years. Properties appear to start trading with a slightly positive  premium, which then decreases over time. This indicates that premiums do not adjust fully as properties are revalued, meaning that realising potential capital gains early is unlikely. To explore this further the following plot compares premiums on initial and latest valuations over time, for individual properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-26-deep-dive-pp-premiums/gif1.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the plot we see that properties enter the market trading at a small premium to both valuations. Over time the relationship between premiums for initial and latest valuation weakens, with several properties trading at negative premiums for both valuations. To get a better idea of the relationship the following plot stratifies by the year a property was made available for resale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-26-deep-dive-pp-premiums/gif2.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we clearly see that when properties enter the market there is a strong correlation between premiums on latest and initial valuations. As properties are revalued we see that premiums on latest valuation do not adjust fully, although this effect varies wildly. This is likely to be driven by external factors such as dividend yield - with high dividend yields commanding a premium. The following interactive plot allows the figures above to be explored in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-26-deep-dive-pp-premiums/fig6.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a final visualisation of this relationship the following plot shows premiums for individual properties over time, stratified by year available for resale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-26-deep-dive-pp-premiums/gif3.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately this dataset was limited by having little additional information about each property, something which is key to understanding premiums. For example, as commented on above, it is likely that much of the variation is drive by dividend yield. However, it is clear that properties are not valued at their latest valuation and that therefore this should not be used to summarise the performance of a portfolio over the short term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a future post I will be exploring premiums further by joining the resale data used above with data on the Property Partner portfolio. The two datasets do not contain a common unique ID by which to link them, meaning that joining them will be less trivial that it should be. Hopefully Property Partner will improve the quality of the data they provide to investors so that analysis can be done more easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any comments, ideas for further projects, or any similar analysis to share please comment below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bonus Plot!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-26-deep-dive-pp-premiums/fig7.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;1000&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Dive; Property Partner July 2017 Open House Resale Data</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/deep-dive-pp-open-house/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/deep-dive-pp-open-house/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As peer to peer lending matures platforms have begun to have increasingly divergent stances on sharing their data, making it increasingly important that their is external pressure on them to improve their data sharing. This blog series will focus on platforms sharing their data, exploring what their data is saying and suggesting possible changes to their releases that would make it easier for investors to gain insights on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first post I will be focussing on data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.propertypartner.co/aboutus#/ourstory&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Property Partner&lt;/a&gt;, which is a property crowd-funding site that started in 2014 and allows investors to buy small stakes in a range of properties. The data I will be using was released as part of Property Partner&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.propertypartner.co/open-house-july-2017/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;July 2017 open house data&lt;/a&gt; blog, and contains information on resale&amp;rsquo;s of their property portfolio. This post will reproduce and update previous work, explore the underlying trends, and suggest possible changes for future releases. All code is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/seabbs/propertypartner&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and the data can be downloaded from this &lt;a href=&#34;https://d2ofd11qqzygs0.cloudfront.net/files/purchases-on-resale-july-2017-open-house.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a starting point I have reproduced a graph of Transactions (£) over time first published &lt;a href=&#34;https://p2pblog.co.uk/property-partner-trading-analysis/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This shows the increase in transactions (£) over time on the resale market, with a continuous increase in volume until early 2016 from which point seasonal variation has dominated. I have also stratified by transaction type, revealing the impact of the recently introduced bidding system, which has steadily increased it&amp;rsquo;s share of transactions month on month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-15-deep-dive-pp-open-house/fig1.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot naturally leads to the following question - is the increase in trading volume driven by an increasing number of trades or by changes in the size of trades being made? The following plot explores this by plotting the number of transactions over time. We see that the early growth in volumes was likely driven by an increasing number of trades but that variation since then is more strongly linked to changes in trade size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-15-deep-dive-pp-open-house/fig2.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we understand how transactions (N) have varied with time we need to explore the underlying trends. The most obvious question is which properties are being traded for the most, and if possible why do these properties have so much turn over? The following plot shows trades by property, stratified by year. For the first year of trading we see that a few properties (as the portfolio was small) dominated the number of trades made. In 2016 trading was spread over more properties but with fewer trades per property. So far for 2017 there has been a greatly reduced number of trades, with trading becoming increasingly homogeneous across the  portfolio. Unfortunately the extract published by Property Partner has little detail about properties so establishing why properties are traded at different rates is difficult. Whilst I could in principle join the various data sets they produce, without a unique ID this would be difficult and prone to errors!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-15-deep-dive-pp-open-house/fig3.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the number of transactions is relatively stable, but the volume of transactions has increased, therefore size of transactions must have changed over time. To explore this I have plotted transactions (£) over time stratified by binned transaction size. As transaction size increases there is greater seasonal variation, which indicates that both large and small traders are key drivers of Property Partner&amp;rsquo;s trading volume with larger trades providing the year on year growth and smaller trades acting to smooth seasonal variability. Since January 2016 there has been little growth in small trades, with larger trades becoming increasingly common. However, the largest trades (£5,000-£49,999) peaked in early 2016 since when they have been decreasing year on year (although this trend is obscured by seasonal variation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-15-deep-dive-pp-open-house/fig4.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the binned transaction sizes used above were helpful in quickly visualising the changes transactions (£) by size they are arbitrary and may be obscuring underlying changes. The following plot explores this by plotting the distribution of transactions sizes within each binned transaction size. This plot contains a large amount of condensed information, the salient points are that mid-size trades (£100-£499) have shifted from being primary around £200 to being relatively equally distributed across the range, large trades (£500-£999) have become increasingly bi-model, and very high value transactions (£20,000+) have become more common as a subset of high value transactions (£5,000-£49,999).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-15-deep-dive-pp-open-house/figure-html/trans-size-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another approach to visualising changing transaction size over time, is to plot the proportion of trades (by number) for each binned transaction size. As indicated in the previous plots, this shows that larger trades have become increasingly common, with the large trades (£1000-£4,999) increasing to 2% of manual trades, and  5% of matched bids in 2017. The most common trade size is still small (£1-£99), but the proportion of very small trades  (£0-£1) has drastically reduced. Matched bids are more likely to be larger transactions with small trades (£1-£99) making up 54% of transactions compared to 68% of manual orders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-15-deep-dive-pp-open-house/fig5.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data released by Property Partner also contains information about the unit price each transaction was made at, and what premium this was against both the latest and original valuation. As this data is provided across all properties in the portfolio a single visualisation of the data may not indicate the underling relationship. A first step is to plot the monthly average (weighted by transaction size) premium on latest valuation for each property in the portfolio, by comparing premiums on latest valuation rather than raw share price properties can be compared against each other. This plot indicates a general
downward trend in premiums but is difficult to interpret due to the number of properties in the portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-15-deep-dive-pp-open-house/fig6.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explore this apparent trend a first step is to look at the trends in premiums across the Property Partner portfolio, using the mean premium across all properties. This indicates that premiums were originally high but have decreased over time, and since the beginning of 2016 have been negative on average. As with transactions (£) seasonal dynamics now appear to dominate with premiums being relatively stable year on year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-15-deep-dive-pp-open-house/fig7.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have averaged across all properties in the Property Partner portfolio the relationship we have identified between year and premium may be confounded by a variety of factors. An obvious question is whether the quality of property purchased by Property Partner has changed over time (if we assume that premium over latest valuation is a good proxy of property quality). The plot below looks at the average weighted premium for properties made available for resale in each year (this is confounded by the rate properties are made available in a given year). From this plot we see that across all years of trading (except 2014) properties start with a small positive premium, which then gradually declines with time. Properties from 2014 have bucked this trend, which is likely due to the novelty of owning a property from the early days of Property Partner. Properties from 2015 have a linear relationship between premium and time, trading increasingly below their valuation. Properties from 2016 suffered a rapid reduction in premium, indicating a possible reduction in property quality, although this has now stabilised. So far properties from 2017 have held positive premiums, with little reduction over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-15-deep-dive-pp-open-house/fig8.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final plot for this blog post I have reproduced another plot from &lt;a href=&#34;https://p2pblog.co.uk/property-partner-trading-analysis/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; (from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://p2pblog.co.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;p2pblog.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;), which is well worth a read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe seamless src=&#34;../../post/2017-09-15-deep-dive-pp-open-house/fig9.html&#34; width = &#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; id=&#34;iframe_container&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see the current state of the Property Partner Portfolio you can explore for youself &lt;a href=&#34;https://public.tableau.com/views/PropertyPartnerPortfolioVisualisation/PropertyPartnerPortfolio?:embed=y&amp;amp;:display_count=yes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;using this Tableau dashboard.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#39;tableauPlaceholder&#39; id=&#39;viz1505484367745&#39; style=&#39;position: relative&#39;&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#&#39;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#39;Property Partner Portfolio &#39; src=&#39;https:&amp;#47;&amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;#47;static&amp;#47;images&amp;#47;Pr&amp;#47;PropertyPartnerPortfolioVisualisation&amp;#47;PropertyPartnerPortfolio&amp;#47;1_rss.png&#39; style=&#39;border: none&#39; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;object class=&#39;tableauViz&#39;  style=&#39;display:none;&#39;&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;host_url&#39; value=&#39;https%3A%2F%2Fpublic.tableau.com%2F&#39; /&gt; &lt;param name=&#39;site_root&#39; value=&#39;&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;name&#39; value=&#39;PropertyPartnerPortfolioVisualisation&amp;#47;PropertyPartnerPortfolio&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;tabs&#39; value=&#39;no&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;toolbar&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;static_image&#39; value=&#39;https:&amp;#47;&amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;#47;static&amp;#47;images&amp;#47;Pr&amp;#47;PropertyPartnerPortfolioVisualisation&amp;#47;PropertyPartnerPortfolio&amp;#47;1.png&#39; /&gt; &lt;param name=&#39;animate_transition&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_static_image&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_spinner&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_overlay&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_count&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;                &lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39;&gt;                    var divElement = document.getElementById(&amp;lsquo;viz1505484367745&amp;rsquo;);                    var vizElement = divElement.getElementsByTagName(&amp;lsquo;object&amp;rsquo;)[0];                    vizElement.style.width=&amp;lsquo;100%&amp;rsquo;;vizElement.style.height=(divElement.offsetWidth*0.75)+&amp;lsquo;px&amp;rsquo;;                    var scriptElement = document.createElement(&amp;lsquo;script&amp;rsquo;);                    scriptElement.src = &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://public.tableau.com/javascripts/api/viz_v1.js&#39;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://public.tableau.com/javascripts/api/viz_v1.js&#39;&lt;/a&gt;;                    vizElement.parentNode.insertBefore(scriptElement, vizElement);                &lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final note whilst it is great that Property Partner releases data this analysis was limited by the quality of the data published. If their is interest in more of these deep data dives then I would suggest contacting the peer to peer platforms that you invest in and asking that a live data extract be made available, without a login or extensive user agreement. This would ideally contain a unique ID for each loan/property etc, information on both primary and secondary market transactions, and metadata about each loan/property; such as location, type, value, etc. If you want to know more about analysis ready data then see &lt;a href=&#34;http://vita.had.co.nz/papers/tidy-data.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing the Pebble Game; a simple app for exploring epidemics and vaccination</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/using-the-pebble-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/using-the-pebble-game/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://seabbs.co.uk/shiny/thepebblegame&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Pebble Game&lt;/a&gt; is a shiny application that simulates a simple game which has been designed  to reflect real world epidemics and the vaccination programmes used to control them. It involves repeatedly drawing pebbles from a bag, which contains two distinct pebble types (to represent vaccinated and unvaccinated individuals). The number of pebbles that are drawn each round is dependent on the number of infect-able (i.e unvaccinated) cases drawn in the previous round, and the infectiousness of the simulated disease. Each game can then be thought of as a single stochastic (with a random element) epidemic, by combining multiple simulations of the game, the dynamics of the system can be understood. Hopefully by playing the game and exploring the app you will gain an insight into how a single vaccination can contribute to protecting the rest of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;playing-a-single-game&#34;&gt;Playing a single game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to understand what is being simulated, hopefully if you have just played the game with me in person you should have a good idea of this! If you haven&amp;rsquo;t played the game with me, and the simple explanation above wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough then see the instructions for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.seabbs.co.uk/shiny/thepebblegame&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;playing the game physcially&lt;/a&gt; (click on the how to play the game tab)- it might even be worth giving it a go at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.seabbs.co.uk/shiny/thepebblegame&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;open the app&lt;/a&gt;. Your screen should then look like this,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/single_game.png&#34; alt=&#34;The game simulation tab from the pebble game app&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should now be looking at 10 simulations of the pebble game, each with 100 pebbles, 60% of pebbles being vaccinated, and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_reproduction_number&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;reproduction number&lt;/a&gt; of 3 (don&amp;rsquo;t know what this is - try hovering over it in the app). These parameters can all be varied (hit the plus in the game parameters box), although if you add more stones or more simulations it may take awhile!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph on the right summarises each simulation, recording the number of pebbles in each generation. You should notice that some paths are darker blue than others, this indicates that multiple simulations traced the same pathway. From this you should see that there are two distinct solutions, a rapid die out of the disease or an epidemic that infects everyone (try varying the parameters to see what effects they have on these &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steady_state&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;steady states&lt;/a&gt;). To get a clearer picture of this try setting the summary statistic to plot to the number of pebbles, this will show how the disease spreads with each generation (known as the epidemic curve).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dark blue line, and shaded ribbon, summarise all your simulations (using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mean&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mean&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confidence_interval&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;95% confidence intervals&lt;/a&gt;), whilst this is helpful it doesn&amp;rsquo;t always tell the full story! This is because if you have diverging solutions, as in this example, a single summary statistic cannot accurately represent either of them and instead represents an overview of the system. This is a well known problem in statistics so watch out for it cropping up elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The table below the graph helps with this problem by providing a variety of summary measures, including the number in each generation, the number of generations, the total number infected, and the percentage of unvaccinated pebbles  that are infected. Each one of these is presented with several measures (mean, median, 25%, and 75% quantiles), this allows you to get an understanding of the distribution (which you can&amp;rsquo;t get from a single point estimate). In this example you should see that mean number of generations is about 7, which parameters effect this measure? Can you vary the parameters so that the mean is still about 7 but the other summary measures change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it is time to investigate an epidemic using the app. A common goal of vaccination programmes is to vaccinate a sufficient proportion of the population that a disease cannot cause an epidemic. The lower bound for this is known as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herd_immunity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;vaccination thresold&lt;/a&gt;, which can often be found mathematically. By varying the parameters of the game you should be able to estimate this threshold! The key question is now what factors influence this vaccination threshold (try varying the game parameters)? Once you&amp;rsquo;ve investigated all the parameters try looking up some real world diseases (for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/roots-of-unity/understand-the-measles-outbreak-with-this-one-weird-number/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;measles&lt;/a&gt;) and seeing how the vaccination threshold of your disease compares to theirs. Why do you think it is different?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparing-diseases&#34;&gt;Comparing diseases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help you further explore the effects of varying parameters on the outcome of the pebble game &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.seabbs.co.uk/shiny/thepebblegame&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the Pebble Game app&lt;/a&gt; has an additional tab (Compare diseases). This lets you simulate two diseases, each with an individual reproduction number, but otherwise using the same parameters. An example, comparing a disease with a reproduction number of 3 and another disease with a reproduction number of 12 can be seen below,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/compare_game.png&#34; alt=&#34;The disease comparision tab from the pebble game app&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The output in this tab is very similar to that in the Play the game tab, but there is now a graph of both diseases, as well as for each disease separately. In this example we see that the second disease has a much lower generation time, than the primary disease. However even for this much slower disease in over 25% of simulations all of the unvaccinated pebbles are still infected!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ideas-for-further-exploration&#34;&gt;Ideas for further exploration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in exploring the pebble game further then here are a few ideas of what to questions to investigate;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What effect does varying the number of simulations have? Are there parameters for which this has a greater impact? If so what implications does this have for real world diseases?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you identify stages of an epidemic by looking at plots of the number of pebbles  in each generation? At which stage is the disease most likely to die out? What does this mean for epidemic control?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What features of epidemics is the Pebble Game not capturing? How do you think these features might influence the results?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this post was a useful introduction to the Pebble Game and to the simple dynamics of infectious disease dynamics and vaccination. If you have any suggests for another blog post, or future developments to the Pebble Game then please comment below or contact me by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/seabbs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.samabbott.co.uk/#contact&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FC Dashboard</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/fcdashboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/fcdashboard/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>idmodelr</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/idmodelr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/idmodelr/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pebble Game</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/thepebblegame/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/thepebblegame/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funding Circle Data Anaylsis</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/funding-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/funding-circle/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>prettypublisher</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/prettypublisher/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/prettypublisher/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>tbinenglanddataclean</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/tbinenglanddataclean/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/project/tbinenglanddataclean/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The temptation of a long loan; Risk and rewards of term length</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/temp-long-loan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/temp-long-loan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a quick update to last weeks post this week we will be using the estimates of bad debt from last week to assess the true risk/rewards of loans at various lengths from the funding circle (FC) loan book. I realised recently that when picking loans my default criteria tends towards picking loans with the lowest percieved risk (i.e lowest risk band) with the highest interest rates possible. This strategy has some interesting consequences in that it preferentially selects long term loans that tend to have higher rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FC surfaces the average bad debt rate by risk band and not by the term of the loan. Whilst this is a simplifying assumption that makes the investing process easier to understand, for it to be true short term loans must be inherantly riskier than long term loans, or the risk of default must be decoupled from time. Both of these assumptions seem unlikely to me,  and in a later past we will be looking further at the lifecourse of loans, but for this week we will simply be using my function for estimating for bad debt individually for each term length. As discussed last time we estimate the percentage of bad debt by comparing the proportion of bad debt, with total debt, accounting for loan size, the principal remaining, and the interest paid on the loan. This approach also has the same caveats as last time in that it does not account for future recoveries by funding circle, and so becomes increasingly inaccurate for more recent loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first identify the possible loan terms available to borrowers in the FC ecosystem, and the number in each category. We see that by far the most common loans terms are those, as might be expected, that are an integer number of years. For clarity we restrict ourselves to looking at these most common loans (6, 12, 24, 48, 36, and 60 months), stratifying by risk band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table: Number of loans by loan length across the funding circle loan book&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Term&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Number of loans&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12916&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7199&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;48&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2435&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1959&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1578&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;244&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;231&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;55&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;48&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;43&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;42&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;35&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-temp-long-loan/figure-html/est_bad_rate_risk-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Estimated bad debt rate, accounting for repayments and the principal remaining, for the 6 most common term lengths straitifed by risk band&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see that the assumption that short term loans are higher risk is only true for loans of 6 months, and for E loans of 12 months, which have a much greater risk of bad debt than all other loans. However these loans are relatively rare so this may be an artifact of low statistical power. For all other loan lengths we see that the risk of bad debt increases, with time with loans that are 36 months and over accounting for the majority of the bad debt in all risk categories. As I have not accounted for the maturity of loans, this apparent trend may be driven by the differing ages of loans in different years. Therefore we repeat the above but now stratify further by year, dropping loans with 6 month terms for clarity. Whilst this does add some variation the overall trend appears to hold with longer term loans having significantly higher proportions of bad debt, this is particularly true of E loans, where 60 month loans have much higher bad debt rates than those with shorter terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An obvious point to note is that FC adjusts interest rates by term length, so that longer term loans have higher rates, this adjustment is obviously to account for the disparity in risk over loan term. In a follow up post I will be using these estimates of bad debt by loan term to evaluate the return on loans of difffernt term lengths to assess whether these adjustments sufficiently account for the increased risk of longer term loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-temp-long-loan/figure-html/bad_debt_2011-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Estimated bad debt by term length stratified by risk band, for 2011&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-temp-long-loan/figure-html/bad_debt_2012-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Estimated bad debt by term length stratified by risk band, for 2012&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-temp-long-loan/figure-html/bad_debt_2013-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Estimated bad debt by term length stratified by risk band, for 2013&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-temp-long-loan/figure-html/bad_debt_2014-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Estimated bad debt by term length stratified by risk band, for 2014&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-temp-long-loan/figure-html/bad_debt_2015-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Estimated bad debt by term length stratified by risk band, for 2015&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-temp-long-loan/figure-html/bad_debt_2016-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Estimated bad debt by term length stratified by risk band, for 2016&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog series is bi-weekly, please comment with suggestions of topics. The code for this post can be found at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/seabbs/funding_circle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the risk of bad debt in the funding circle loanbook</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/fc-risk-bad-debt/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/fc-risk-bad-debt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are again looking at the peer to peer (P2P) loan book for funding circle (FC), with the focus being the variation in return based on portfolio composition and diversification. FC states that the average return on investment is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fundingcircle.com/uk/statistics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;6.6%&lt;/a&gt;,  with 93% of investors that invested in more than 100 companies, with a maximum exposure of 1% earning 5% or more. The original purpose of this blog was to look at various portfolio&amp;rsquo;s and estimate the risk that they carry for the investor. A key component of this is an understanding of the bad debt rate and it&amp;rsquo;s variation over time, which proved more complex to estimate than expected. This post will be looking in detail at various measures of the bad debt rate and raising questions for future posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FC states that the average bad debt rate across all risk categories is 1.8% (after bad debt recovery), and that 42% of all defaulted loans are recovered. Across the platform the average risk of default for each risk band is 0.6% for A+ loans,  1.5%    for A loans, 2.3% for B loans, 3.3% for C loans, 5.0% for D loans, and 8.0% for E loans. In order to optimise a portfolio, that both minimises risk and maximises profit a complete understanding of these risk levels is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FC estimates bad debt rates by taking the actual bad debt rate by loan amount, incorporating the estimated bad debt rate for years that have not matured, and then including the expected recoveries that are expected from each year of origination. Whilst the source of these estimates has not been surfaced it is likely that the estimated bad debt for loans that have not matured is estimated from previous years, whilst the the FC statistics page states that average recoveries are 42% of the defaulted amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explore these assumptions we start by roughly calculating the bad debt rate, looking solely at the number of loans that defaulted in a given year and comparing this to the total number of loans. This is obviously a flawed approach as it does not account for loan size, repayments, recoveries, or the maturity of the loan. However it represents a crude initial estimate of the default rate in each risk category. This approach yields far higher estimates of bad debt, than those estimated by FC. To account for the variability in loan size we repeat the above steps but this time account for loan size. This approach can further be refined by accounting for loan repayments prior to the loan defaulting. There are multiple approaches to this, the first of which is to adjust for the amount recovered from defaulted loans, another option is to instead estimate the proportion of bad debt from the principal remaining. Finally by looking at the term length of the loan, and the number of repayments made I can estimate the amount of interest payed on a loan and use this to offset the loss made by the loan defaulting. This assumes that interest is payed on the total loan amount as opposed to the amount outstanding (therefore this measure will slightly underestimate the levels of bad debt).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-fc-risk-bad-debt/figure-html/estimate_loanbook_bad_debit-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Estimated bad debt by year, using various methodologies&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this approach we find higher estimates for bad debt using every approach than that estimated by funding circle, this may be due to the differing approaches used or from user error! Reassuringly the most complex approach, that includes the interest payed on loans and the amount payed of the principal gives the closest estimates to those given by funding circle. I have made no adjustments for loans that have not matured, so decreasing bad debt overtime does not necessarily indicate a trend. I have also not accounted for future recoveries by FC which may substantially reduce the proportion of bad debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To investigate this further I have estimated the bad debt rate for each risk category using all the approaches discussed above. As can be seen below this yields estimates of bad debt that are greater than those estimated by FC, interestingly this is not true for E risk loans, indicating that year of loan origination may be a factor (as E loans are the most recently offered).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-fc-risk-bad-debt/figure-html/est_bad_rate_risk-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now focussing on just using the most complex model for bad debt, we see that early investors suffered from poor risk categorisation by funding circle with high default rates across all risk bands. This indicates that holding newly introduced products to term may result in higher than expected loses, although cash back programs may compensate. Bad debt then stabilises indicating successful classification of loans into credit bands. However, these estimates are still higher than those estimated by funding circle, though this maybe due to the exclusion of future recoveries from my estimation model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-fc-risk-bad-debt/figure-html/est_bad_rate_risk_year-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table: Bad debt by year for B (Below average risk) loans&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt by loan size&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted by recoveries&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted for principal remaining&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted for loan repayment and principal remaining&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2016&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0 v                              1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table: Bad debt by year for A+ (Very low risk) loans&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt by loan size&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted by recoveries&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted for principal remaining&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted for loan repayment and principal remaining&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2016&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table: Bad debt by year for C (Average risk) loans&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt by loan size&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted by recoveries&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted for principal remaining&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted for loan repayment and principal remaining&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2016&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table: Bad debt by year for D loans&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt by loan size&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted by recoveries&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted for principal remaining&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted for loan repayment and principal remaining&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2016&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table: Bad debt by year for E loans&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt by loan size&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted by recoveries&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted for principal remaining&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bad debt adjusted for loan repayment and principal remaining&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2016&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In future blogs I will be further exploring loan risk and attempting to investigate investor risk in a variety of portfolio structures. I am particularly interested in exploring the default rate of loans over time, as increasing risk may indicate some beneficial strategies. Let me know if you have any blog ideas, some potential areas are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding estimated default for newly acquired loans, coupled with a range of scenarios for loan recoveries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Loan default risk over the loan period&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comparison of property interest only loans to an ordinary FC loan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The trade off between loan length and interest rates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portfolio structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately future analysis may be limited by the limited dataset released by FC, as key dates are not including in the public loan book. Hopefully if there is sufficient pressure more data will be released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog series will be bi-weekly, please comment with suggestions of topics. The code for this post can be found at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/seabbs/funding_circle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualising the funding circle loanbook</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/2017-06-10-vis-fc-loanbook-md/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/2017-06-10-vis-fc-loanbook-md/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first in a series of blog posts looking at P2P lenders, which will be aimed at surfacing more details about the structures of their loan books. I hope to expand this series by looking at optimal strategies, predictive modelling, and interactive data science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2005, with the launch of &lt;a href=&#34;www.zopa.co.uk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Zopa&lt;/a&gt; P2P companies have provided a middle path between cash holdings, and investing in stocks and shares. Funding circle, which was launched in 2010, has currently facilitated over £1 Billion in loans to British businesses. It has also returned on average 6.6% after the exclusion of bad debt, fees etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The platform offers small, and medium businesses loans of up to £1 million, for up to 60 months. Whole or fractional loans are then purchased by individuals/institutions. Since September 2015 loans have been offered with fixed rates determined by FC using the risk category of the company, and the loan terms. There is also a secondary market where individuals can sell loan parts, for a 0.25% fee, at a premium, at parity, or at a discount. Prior to September 2016 loans were auctioned with no fixed rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FC allows the investor to hand pick each loan that they invest in, and the level of your exposure. However investors can also use an automated auto-bid tool that automatically buys loans, on both the primary and secondary markets, based on pre-set options specified by the investor. These include selecting risk levels to lend to, selecting rates to buy loans on the secondary market, and specifying a target maximum exposure to any single loan. These two system lead to a tension, with those that are hand-picking loans being potentially able to manipulate the auto-bid algorithm acting for other investors. As part of this blog series I will be looking further into these strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for some simple visualisations of the FC loan book, with the first step being to load the required packages (unhash for first run).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;#install.packages(&#39;tidyverse&#39;)
library(tidyverse)

#install.packages(&#39;lubridate&#39;)
library(lubridate)

#install.packages(&#39;stargazer&#39;)
library(stargazer)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to load in the data and display the variable names:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;## File path of loanbook 
df_path  &amp;lt;- &#39;~/data/Funding_circle/loanbook.csv&#39;

## Load data with miss spec as N/A
loanbook &amp;lt;- read_csv(df_path, na=&#39;N/A&#39;)

## var to factors
factor_list &amp;lt;- c(&#39;status&#39;, &#39;credit_band&#39;, &#39;loan_purpose&#39;, &#39;sector&#39;, &#39;business_type_name&#39;, &#39;region_name&#39;, &#39;whole_loan&#39;, &#39;repayment_type&#39;, &#39;security_taken&#39;)
                 
                 
format_factors &amp;lt;- function(factor_list, df){
                   for (var in factor_list)
                   {
                     df[[var]] &amp;lt;- factor(df[[var]])
                   }
                   
                   return(df)
}
loanbook &amp;lt;- format_factors(factor_list, loanbook)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We print the simple summary of the data as a first step (hidden for brevity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;summary(loanbook)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the loan book has evolved with time an immediate question is how the number of loans, at each risk level has changed with time. Across all risk bands we see that year on year loan acceptances have increased, with 2016 showing by far the largest growth. Notably we see the introduction of D loans in 2013, and the introduction of E loans in 2015. The vast majority of funding circle loans are with &amp;lsquo;low risk&amp;rsquo; borrowers (i.e A, and A+), although the number of risky loans is now greater than the entire loan book in 2014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt; #Plot incidence - by year
loanbook %&amp;gt;% 
    mutate(month = floor_date(loan_accepted_date, &amp;quot;month&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
        count(month, credit_band) %&amp;gt;% 
        ggplot(aes(x=month, y=n, fill=credit_band)) + 
          geom_area() -&amp;gt; p1
p1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-vis-fc-loanbook-md/figure-html/offer-year-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now aggregate by month so that we can understand patterns of loan acceptances across the risk bands. For all risk bands we see that there is a increasing trend towards the end of the year, with the fewest loans originated in April, and March, indicating that this may not be a good time to move funds into FC, and consequently this may lead to an up-tick in the secondary market. E loans show the strongest growth in the second half of the year - however this may be an artefact of their relatively recent introduction, which maybe responsible for this apparent trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;loanbook %&amp;gt;%
        mutate(month = month(loan_accepted_date, label=TRUE)) %&amp;gt;%
        ggplot(aes(x=month)) + 
          geom_bar() + 
            facet_wrap(~credit_band, scale=&#39;free&#39;) + 
            theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle=45)) -&amp;gt; p2
p2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-vis-fc-loanbook-md/figure-html/monthly-risk-band-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally we aggregate by day. There is limited evidence here that loan acceptances vary between weekdays, with a slight upward tick mid week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;loanbook %&amp;gt;%
        mutate(day = wday(loan_accepted_date, label=TRUE)) %&amp;gt;%
        ggplot(aes(x=day)) + 
          geom_bar() + 
            facet_wrap(~credit_band, scale=&#39;free&#39;) + 
            theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle=90)) -&amp;gt; p5
p5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-vis-fc-loanbook-md/figure-html/daly-risk-band-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To link these trends to demand from investors we plot the average interest rate of each accepted loan. We see that average rates are linked with supply for historic loans that were accepted using the biding system. However as expected since the introduction of the fixed rate loan system supply is now uncoupled from price, this presents possible advantages for the hand-picking investor who can buy loans at times of peak supply and sell loans at times of scarcity at a premium on the secondary market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;plot_monthly_risk_band &amp;lt;- function(df, years)
{
  df %&amp;gt;%
        mutate(month = month(loan_accepted_date, label=TRUE)) %&amp;gt;%
           mutate(year = year(loan_accepted_date)) %&amp;gt;% 
                filter(year %in% years) %&amp;gt;% 
                   group_by(month, credit_band, year) %&amp;gt;% 
                      summarise(`Avg interest rate`=mean(interest_rate)) %&amp;gt;% 
                          ggplot(aes(x=month, y=`Avg interest rate`, shape=credit_band, color=credit_band, fill=credit_band, group=credit_band))  +
                              geom_line() +
                                facet_wrap(~year, scale=&#39;free&#39;) +
                                  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle=45)) -&amp;gt; p
  return(p)
}

p3 &amp;lt;- plot_monthly_risk_band(loanbook, c(2010:2013))
p4 &amp;lt;- plot_monthly_risk_band(loanbook, c(2014:2016))
p3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-vis-fc-loanbook-md/figure-html/monthly-risk-band-split-by-year-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;p4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../post/2017-06-10-vis-fc-loanbook-md/figure-html/monthly-risk-band-split-by-year-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog series will be bi-weekly, please comment with suggestions of topics. The code for this post can be found at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/clapping-bunny/funding_circle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
