<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Deep dive on Sam Abbott</title>
    <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/tags/deep-dive/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Deep dive on Sam Abbott</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Sam Abbott</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.samabbott.co.uk/tags/deep-dive/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Dive; Premiums on Valuation in the Property Partner Portfolio</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/deep-dive-pp-premiums/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/deep-dive-pp-premiums/</guid>
      <description>Previously I have looked at visualising the Property Partner portfolio using tableau, and explored their resale date from July 2017. In this post I will be exploring the August Open House resale data focussing on property premiums over both initial and latest valuation. The code for this post is available here.
Property Partner advertises returns by combining both projected capital and rental returns. Properties are held for 5 years at which point any capital gain can be realised.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Dive; Property Partner July 2017 Open House Resale Data</title>
      <link>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/deep-dive-pp-open-house/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.samabbott.co.uk/post/deep-dive-pp-open-house/</guid>
      <description>As peer to peer lending matures platforms have begun to have increasingly divergent stances on sharing their data, making it increasingly important that their is external pressure on them to improve their data sharing. This blog series will focus on platforms sharing their data, exploring what their data is saying and suggesting possible changes to their releases that would make it easier for investors to gain insights on their own.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>